José Jair Santanna

Ph.D. Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

Programming

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

Professional Objective

A research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation that improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

Education

2013-Now	Doctor	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon"	
2010–2012	Master in Computer Science "A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain of this work generated a product still in usuand Research Network (RNP) (Link: http:	se by the Brazilian National Education
2005–2010	Bachelor in Computer Engineer "A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Proto	Federal University of Pará, Brazil ocol in a Experimental Mesh Network."

Experience

2016

Technical Adviser

	tation Center	The Netherlands	
	For the production of a yearly report on "Cyber metrics 2016:	: DDoS and Mal-	
	ware" requested by the Dutch Ministry of Justice.		
2016	To the Yokohama National University	Japan	
	For the production of a report about "Reflection & Amplification requested by the Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Cor		

To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

Assistant Professor

2012-2013	University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)	Santa Cruz do Sul, Brazil
	Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach	the following courses:
	Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems	

Guest Lecturer

2015 & 2016	Product Design to Online Business (course)	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	Audience: bachelor students of industrial engine technology.	eering and business information
2015	Network Security (course) Audience: master and bachelor students of cogineer, and telematics from the University of Tomembers of ICT labs.	

2015 **Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor)**University of Twente, The Netherlands
Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research
Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Universität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

Software Developer

2015–Now **Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)**

Link: http://bit.ly/ddos_db

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP)

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application sponsored by Eletronorte, subsidiary of the major Brazilian

power utility (Eletrobrás). Language: C#.Net & mySQL

Student Supervisor

[M.Sc. Degree] Joey de Vries [Cum Laude], Justyna Chromik [Cum Laude], Wouter de Vries, Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak, Max Kerkers, Dirk Maan, Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

International Conference Reviewer

IFIP Networking (2014–2016), IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (2014 & 2016), Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium (2013 & 2014), IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management (2015), International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (2015), International Conference on Network and Service Management (2013–2015), EUNICE Conference (2013) & IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications(2011)

Awards

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch'	(1 st Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 rd Place)		CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award	Autonomous Infrastructure,	Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Bra	zilian Symposium on Comp	uter Networks and Distributed Systems
2010	Student Award (3 rd Place)	Computer En	gineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

Communication Skills

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (see in: http://www.slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

2015	Oral Presentation	at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).
2015	Oral Presentation t	to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).
2015	Oral Presentation	to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).
2013 & 2015	Oral Presentation	at the 31 th and 36 th IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

Scientific Appendix

Description of Ph.D. Research

Publications